Arafat Hassan



hassanarafat@yahoo.com



linkedin.com/in/arafat-hassan-3364b2146

Summary

Earned a Bachelor of Science (BS) focused in Geographic Information Science and a minor focusing in City and Regional Planning from The Ohio State University. Skilled in administering/managing databases and using GIS/ visualization related softwares such as ESRI ArcGIS tools, ERDAS Imagine, QGIS, Tableau, etc. Continuously learning programming languages such as JAVA, HTML, Arcade Expressions, Python, R Programming, etc. Extensively experienced in Microsoft Office (Excel, Word, Powerpoint, etc.), Google Drive, ETL process, retail, and customer service.

Experience

Systems Analyst/GIS Administrator

City of Westerville

Feb 2022 - Present (1 year)

- Develop short and long-range plans, goals, objectives and priorities to improve city's operational efficiency and effectiveness for GIS development and integrations
- Communicate with GIS users to determine current and future needs, and implements recommendations such as building a custom printing widget for WebGIS
- Maintain and monitor the health of the GIS servers including performing monthly updates for both ArcGIS Enterprise and ArcGIS Online
- Develop, administer, and maintain GIS web sites and applications for the internet and intranet
- Performs continuous updates of city's core GIS data and web site information
- Communicate with the general public, vendors, management, and contractors in order to coordinate GIS projects and administer the use of data such as Tyler Technologies: New World, FuturaGIS, etc.
- Represent the GIS team on committees and task forces by serving as a technical advisor in the exchange of information or in addressing specific needs
- Prepare, process, and review written documents pertaining to GIS to ensure compliance with departmental policies and procedures
- Prioritize and track time-sensitive projects and assignments to ensure timely completion
- Coordinate and oversee various special projects and/or presentations in support of the GIS system including transitioning from current aerial imagery provider, giving GIS presentation at the Citizens Academy, etc.
- Establish and maintain effective working relationships with superiors, fellow workers, and vendor's representatives
- Review programs, white-papers, research papers, attend training courses, attend GIS Steering Committee meetings, etc. to develop innovative approaches to problem solving and to make recommendations
- Develop, document, and provide GIS standards, training and guidance for GIS users within the City of Westerville

MISOURCE GIS Technician

NiSource

Jan 2021 - Feb 2022 (1 year 2 months)

- Analyze design capital project completion information by reviewing proper pressure tests, materials, and facilities to assure compliance with proposed engineering designs, company policies, practices, standards and other applicable codes
- Update/maintain GIS and work management system to accurately reflect gas system updates using given project as-built and related documentations
- Execute capital projects including providing new gas service to new customers, public roadway improvements and relocations, gas system improvement and maintenance in a timely manner that adheres with the department metrics
- Provide technical assistance and build strong relationship through communication and collaboration with Field Engineering, Construction, M&R, and Field Operation staff
- Proactively collaborate with leaders, co-workers, and key business partners with planning group goals, objectives, and priorities to exceed department metrics
- Assist co-workers with executing their capital projects
- Guide Field Operation staff to provide accurate information for non-capital work to capital work
- Actively reaching out to participate on upcoming department projects such as beta testing migration from ArcMap to ArcGIS Pro and accurately mapping customer service lines
- Continuously learning about upcoming GIS news and tools to keep up with the industry standards and expand personal knowledge



🔰 GIS Analyst/Engineering Technician I

City of Canton, Ohio

May 2019 - Jan 2021 (1 year 9 months)

- Maintain and update enterprise GIS databases with new/existing water distribution system data in a Geometric Network
- Perform quality assurance for the water distribution system data from multiple sources (field workers, historical records, engineering drawing, and AutoCAD drawings)
- Initiator of the organizational system that keeps records of the waterline projects including creating As-Builts drawings and end of the year cost reports
- Utilization of ArcGIS Pro to append data between databases
- Apply hosted feature layers in ArcGIS Pro to append next day assignments in Workforce for ArcGIS of water assets verification for interns
- Generates custom feature layers in ArcGIS Pro through digitizing to then be published as a web layer in ArcGIS Online for future presentations
- Creates web maps and applications such as dashboards by utilizing ArcGIS Online
- Utilization of Workforce for ArcGIS, Collector, and Survey123 app to perform GPS data collection
- Performs in field data collection of GPS data from new/replaced water valves, fire hydrants, curb stops, and fittings using Trimble products
- Collaborates with supervisors to plan current or next GIS project/agenda
- Provides teaching and mentorship to GIS interns
- Assists with tech support to field workers and help fix troubleshoots with the county GIS Department



GIS Planner Intern

Delaware County, Ohio

Sep 2018 - Apr 2019 (8 months)

- Assisted with converting and modifying county shapefiles from ArcView 3.2 to ArcMap 10.6 using "Import from ArcView" ArcMap extension
- Store texts/annotations including road names in a geodatabase with correct fonts and its size

- Match queries, map symbols, shapefile names, legends, title, scale bar, neatlines, north arrow in ArcMap with ArcView
- Combined converted map with updated geodatabase text annotations to export it to a PDF file
- Collaborated with supervisors to update and maintain the county maps such as new zoning, removing silvers or gaps of polygons

Retail Sales Consultant

Sprint

Dec 2017 - Apr 2019 (1 year 5 months)

- Assisted customers with their cellular needs through creating bundles that works for them.
- Exceeded key performance objectives, including sales and customer satisfaction goals

Team Member

ZAGG, Inc.

Jun 2016 - Dec 2017 (1 year 7 months)

- Collaborated with supervisors and coworkers to train new employees
- Managed store opening or closing operations, including auditing cash register and counting inventory

Barista

Columbus State Community College

Jan 2015 - Jun 2016 (1 year 6 months)

- Served customers with coffee drinks in a timely manner
- Managed store opening or closing operations

Server Assistant

Cameron Mitchell Restaurants

May 2014 - Jun 2016 (2 years 2 months)

- Assisted servers with tasks such as delivering food to serve guests better
- Organized tables in an appealing way by ensuring utensils, glasses are clean for next service

Service Champ

Taco Bell

Jun 2011 - Sep 2014 (3 years 4 months)

- Implemented a plan to serve the customers in a timelier manner at drive thru
- Trained new employees and supported existing employees with their tasks

CSL Plasma Reception Technician

CSL Plasma

Jul 2013 - Nov 2013 (5 months)

- Assisted qualified donors in completing the screening process
- Educated new donors on the use of therapeutic products made from donated plasma

Education

1 The Ohio State University

Geographic Information Science and Cartography, City and Regional Planning, Geographic Information Science, City and Regional Planning 2016 - 2018

Columbus State Community College

Associate of Science - AS, General Studies 2013 - 2016

Licenses & Certifications

- ArcGIS Enterprise: Configuring a Base Deployment Esri 50158813
- esri ArcGIS Enterprise: Administration Workflows Esri 50158893
- Foundations: Data, Data, Everywhere Coursera
 PWN9VKA5VCFW
- Ask Questions to Make Data-Driven Decisions Coursera GUN73XEDMYHQ
- Prepare Data for Exploration Coursera
 57VXZZPLSPUZ
- Process Data from Dirty to Clean Coursera SWHBDTQ95J9F
- Analyze Data to Answer Questions Coursera YL7JRF3U26HZ
- Share Data Through the Art of Visualization Coursera
 A889NE8UPESY
- Futura GIS II Futura Systems
- Data Analysis with R Programming Coursera
 L5EWBZE4WLCS

Getting Started with the FME Platform - Safe Software

Skills

MATLAB • R (Programming Language) • Tableau • Data Conversion • ArcGIS Products • HTML • Python (Programming Language) • Databases • Global Positioning System (GPS) • Microsoft SQL Server